A Guide to the E. Alvin Gerhardt papers, 1970-1981
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
E. Alvin Gerhardt papers, 1970-1981
The Library of Virginia
43514
1.8 cu. ft. and 4 boxes
E. Alvin Gerhardt
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Jennifer Weiskotten, Virignia Association of Museums, Richmond, Virginia.
Biographical Information
Earl Alvin Gerhardt was born 15 October 1930 in Lynchburg, Virginia, to Earl Alvin Gerhardt and Georgia Burton Gerhardt. E. Alvin Gerhardt graduated from Davidson College in 1951, then served in the United States army during the Korean War. Gerhardt returned to Lynchburg after the war to work in his family's business, Lynchburg Hosiery Mills. While in Lynchburg, he served as the volunteer director of the Lynchburg Historical Museum. He was president of the Lynchburg Historical Society in 1970-1971, and was a founding member of the Virginia History Federation (now the Virginia Association of Museums), serving as its president in 1972-1973. After the family business was sold, Gerhardt entered the Cooperstown Graduate Program, State University of New York, and received his master's degree in 1974. That same year, he became the professional director of Rocky Mount, a historic home in Piney Flats, Tennessee. In 1992, he became the Director of Museum Program and Studies at Tusculum College. He retired in 2000. Gerhardt and his wife Salley T. Flournoy Gerhardt had four children. E. Alvin Gerhardt died 5 February 2012.
Scope and Content
Papers, 1970-1981, of E. Alvin Gerhardt (1930-2012) of Lynchburg, Virginia, and Piney Flats, Tennessee, consisting of agendas, brochures, clippings, minutes, newsletters, and other papers regarding his work in historical organizations. Majority of collection concerns the celebration of the Bicentennial of American independence in Virginia and across the nation.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into the following series:
Series I: Virginia Independence Bicentennial Commission, 1970-1981.
Series II: American Revolution Bicentennial Commission, 1969-1976.
Series III: Lynchburg Bicentennial Commission, 1971-1974.
Series IV: Virginia Bicentennial papers, 1971-1977.
Series V: Bicentennial publications, 1968-1977.
Series VI: Bicentennial general papers, 1971-1976.
Series VII: Lynchburg organizations, 1962-1973.
Series VIII: Virginia organizations, 1973-1975.
Contents List
- Series I: Virginia Independence Bicentennial Commission, 1970-1981., Extent: 1 box. (Box 1)
  Virginia Independence Bicentennial Commission, 1970-1981, contains agendas, articles of incorporation, correspondence, minutes, newsletters, proposals, reports, and other papers relating to the commission's work planning Virginia's Bicentennial celebration.
  - Agendas, minutes, and related papers, 1 December 1970-15 January 1971. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Agendas, minutes, and related papers, 11 June 1971-27 August 1971. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Statewide forum, 17 September 1971. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Agendas, minutes, and related papers, 8 October 1971-6 December 1971. (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Agendas, minutes, and related papers, 7 January 1972-13 April 1972. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Agendas, minutes, and related papers, 14 July 1972-11 September 1972. (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Agendas, minutes, and related papers, 23 October 1972-29 December 1972. (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Agendas, minutes, and related papers, February 1973-16 April 1973. (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Agendas, minutes, and related papers, 4 June 1973-20 August 1973. (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Agendas, minutes, and related papers, 12 October 1973-5 November 1973. (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Agendas, minutes, and related papers, 11 January 1974-12 March 1974. (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Agendas, minutes, and related papers, 12 April 1974-31 May 1974. (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Agendas, minutes, and related papers, 11 July 1974-15 November 1974. (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Agendas, minutes, and related papers, 20 March 1975, undated. (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Articles of incorporation, 1972. (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Virginia Independence Bicentennial News and Bicentennial Newsletter, 1973. (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Bicentennial Newsletter, 1974. (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Bicentennial Newsletter, 1975. (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Bicentennial Newsletter, 1976. (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Bicentennial Newsletter, 1977. (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Bicentennial Newsletter, 1978. (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Bicentennial Newsletter, 1979. (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Bicentennial Newsletter, 1980. (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - '81 News, 1980-1981. (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Budget exhibit, 1974-1976. (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Report to the Governor and the General Assembly (House document no. 8), 1973. (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Bicentennial proposal from Haycox Photoramic, Inc., 1 December 1970. (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - A Coordinated Graphic Program for Three Bicentennial Visitor Centers, proposal from Design and Production Incorporated, March 1973. (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Proposal from David M. Pesanelli, Inc., [June] 1973. (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Bicentennial history and youth, 1973. (Box 1, Folder 30)
- Series II: American Revolution Bicentennial Commission, 1969-1976., Extent: 1 box. (Box 2)
  American Revolution Bicentennial Commission, 1969-1976, contains articles, booklets, correspondence, documents, inventories, newsletters, posters, proposals, and other papers regarding the national Bicentennial celebration.
  - Bicentennial Newsletter, 1973. (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Bicentennial Times, volume 1, issues 2-4, 1974. (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Bicentennial Times, volume 1, issues 5-6, 8, 1974. (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Bicentennial Times, volume 2, December 1975. (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Bicentennial Times, volume 3, January, March 1976. (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Bicentennial Times, volume 3, April-June 1976. (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Bicentennial Times, volume 3, July 1976 (2 copies). (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Bicentennial Times, volume 3, August-October 1976. (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Bicentennial Times, volume 3, November-December 1976. (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Official documents of the American Revolution Bicentennial Commission. (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - We're having a birthday...let's celebrate! July 1975. (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Bicentennial Projects: An Inventory of Ethnic, Historical and Cultural Societies. (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - American Revolution Bicentennial Symbol: Guidelines for Auhtorized Usage and Official Graphics Standards Manual. (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - A Proposal to the American Revolution Bicentennial Commission from the District of Columbia Bicentennial Commission, the Maryland Bicentennial Commission, and the Virginia Independence Bicentennial Commission, September 1969. (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Toward a Meaningful Bicentennial, proposal from the Philadelphia 1976 Bicentennial Corporation, 24 September 1969. (Box 2, Folder 15)
- Series III: Lynchburg Bicentennial Commission, 1971-1974., Extent: 2 boxes. (Box 2-3)
  Lynchburg Bicentennial Commission, 1971-1974, contains address lists, agendas, articles, correspondence, forms, memorandums, minutes, notes, presentations, reports, resolutions, and other papers relating to the commission's work planning Lynchburg's Bicentennial celebration.
  - Minutes and related papers, December 1971-February 1972. (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Minutes and related papers, April-October 1972. (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Minutes and related papers, January-March 1973. (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Minutes and related papers, April-May 1973. (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Minutes and related papers, June-August 1973. (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Papers, 1971. (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Papers, 1972. (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Papers, 1973. (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Papers, 1974. (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Articles, 1971-1973. (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Series IV: Virginia Bicentennial papers, 1971-1977., Extent: 1 box. (Box 3)
  Virginia Bicentennial papers, 1971-1977, contains agendas, clippings, correspondence, letterhead stationery, proposals, and other papers from Bicentennial committees in Albemarle-Charlottesville, Alexandria, Richmond, and Williamsburg-James City County. Series also includies standards, 1972, for the Bicentennial Celebration on the Virginia Peninsula and report, 1977, on the Bicentennial Celebration in Virginia, from the office of Governor Mills Godwin.
  - Albemarle-Charlottesville American Independence Bicentennial Commission proposal, 1971. (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Alexandria Bicentennial Commission papers, 1972. (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Richmond Independence Bicentennial Commission letterhead stationery. (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Williamsburg-James City County Bicentennial Commission papers, 1975. (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Standards for the Bicentennial Celebration on the Peninsula, 1972. (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Celebration of the Bicentennial in Virginia, report from the office of Governor Mills Godwin, 1977. (Box 3, Folder 11)
- Series V: Bicentennial publications, 1968-1977., Extent: 2 boxes. (Box 3-4)
  Bicentennial publications, 1968-1977, consisting of articles, bibiographies, books, brochures, clippings, magazines, newsletters, pamphlets, and other papers regarding the Bicentennial celebration in Virginia and across the nation. Also includes catalogs and order forms for Bicentennial-themed merchandise.
  - American Issues, June-August 1975. (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - American Issues, September-December 1975. (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - American Issues, January-February 1976. (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - American Issues, papers, June-July 1975. (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - An American Tragicomedy: Planning for the Big Bash for 1976, Saturday Review, 1 July 1972. (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - The Bicentennial Chronicle and Colonial Heritage, 1970-1971 (both titles), 1972 (Colonial Heritage only--Summer 1972). (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Time Bicentennial issues (Independence! and The New Nation), 1975, 1976. (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - The Unofficial Bicentennial Joke Book, 1976. (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Bibliographies of literature on the American Revolution, 1968, 1976. (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Virginia Bicentennial brochures and pamphlets. (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - United States Bicentennial pamphlets. (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Clippings, 1972. (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Clippings, 1973. (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Clippings, 1974. (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Clippings, 1976. (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Clippings, undated. (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Catalogs and order forms. (Box 4, Folder 6)
- Series VI: Bicentennial general papers, 1971-1976., Extent: 1 box. (Box 4)
  Bicentennial general papers, 1971-1976, contains of articles, booklets, correspondence, pamphlets, resolutions, statements, and other papers from the New York State American Revolution Bicentennial; the United States World Exposition in Boston, Massachusetts; and the Michigan Historical Commission. Papers include magazine abstract, correspondence, and pamphlet about celebrating the Bicentennial. Also includes Bicentennial napkins.
  - New York State American Revolution Bicentennial Commission papers, 1972-1976. (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - U.S. Bicentennial World Exposition, Boston, 1976. (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Miscellaneous papers, 1971-1973, undated. (Box 4, Folder 9)
- Series VII: Lynchburg organizations, 1962-1973., Extent: 1 box. (Box 4)
  Lynchburg organizations, 1962-1973, contains agendas, articles of consolidation, brochures, bylaws, certificates, clippings, correspondence, directories, histories, minutes, programs, reports, and other papers regarding the Lynchburg Sesquicentennial Association, the Jones Memorial Library, the Lynchburg Historical Society, the Lynchburg Historical Foundation, Lynchburg Historical Museum, and the Greater Lynchburg Chamber of Commerce.
  - Lynchburg Sesqui-centennial Association papers, 1 October 1936. (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Jones Memorial Library papers, 1962, 1973. (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Lynchburg Historical Society papers, 1965-1973. (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Lynchburg Historical Foundation papers, 1973, undated. (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Lynchburg Historical Museum (Lynchburg Museum of Living History), 1973, undated. (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Directory of Community Organizations, Greater Lynchburg Chamber of Commerce, August 1973. (Box 4, Folder 15)
- Series VIII: Virginia organizations, 1973-1975., Extent: 1 box. (Box 4)
  Virginia organizations, 1973-1975, contains booklets, correspondence, guides, memorandums, and other papers regarding the Virginia History Federation, the Central Virginia Planning Commission, the University of Virginia Library's manuscript collections relating to Lynchburg, the Virginia State Library, and the Science Museum of Virginia.
  - Virginia History Federation papers, 1973-1974. (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Central Virginia Planning District Commission papers, 1973-1975. (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - University of Virginia, Alderman Library, papers relating to Lynchburg, 1973. (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Virginia State Library and the Science Museum of Virginia papers, 1973. (Box 4, Folder 19)